Marcel Breuer Papers
Marcel Breuer Papers
- Project records
  - NEUMANN HOUSE, POOL HOUSE, Croton-on-Hudson, NY (1955-1974). Marcel Breuer and Associates, Architects. [Residential, Single]
    - Photographs, 37
      - Drainage and sealant features, construction, detail; black and white photographs; 16 (Box 63, Folder 9)
      - Pool location at existing house, existing conditions, exterior view; black and white photograph; 1 (Box 63, Folder 9)
  - NEW ENGLAND MERCHANTS' BANK BUILDING, COMPETITION, Boston, MA (1964) (not built). Marcel Breuer and Herbert Beckhard, Architects. [Commercial], (Alternate names: Boston Competition)
    - Drawings, 162
      - Design development drawings and sketches, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); includes diagrammatic sketches, site plans, floor plans, elevations, sections, wall panel and column variations, parking studies; 134 (Tube 625, Tube 634)
      - Presentation set: Typical office floor, 3-20 (Dwg. No. P-1); typical office floor, 21-22 (Dwg. No. P-2); typical office floor, 23-40 (Dwg. No. P-3); lower mechanical floor plan - 2nd floor (Dwg. No. P-4); upper mechanical floor plan - 41st floor (Dwg. No. P-5); roof plan - cooling towers (Dwg. No. P-6); ground floor and site plan (Dwg. No. P-7); bearing wall panel details (Dwg. No. P-8); non bearing wall panel and corner column details (Dwg. No. P-9); north and south tower elevations (Dwg. No. P-10); east and west tower elevations (Dwg. No. P-11); sections through lowest floors (Dwg. No. P-12); basement plans (Dwg. No. P-13); details elevations of lower floors (Dwg. No. P-14); west wall sections (Dwg. No. P-15), presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); multiple copies of some sheets; 11 originals and 5 prints; 16 (Tube 1091)
      - Presentation set: Situation plan - phasing diagram (Dwg. No. 1); plaza level plan (Dwg. No. 2); circulation diagram - exterior lighting plan (Dwg. No. 3); floor plans (Dwg. No. 4); elevations (Dwg. Nos. 5, 6); sections (Dwg. No. 7); elevation details (Dwg. No. 8); typical wall details (Dwg. No. 9), presentation drawings (reproductions); multiple copies of some sheets; 10 (Tube 1091)
      - Site plan: Dwg. No. SK1, presentation drawings (reproductions); 2 copies, 1 with color annotations; 2 (Tube 1091)
  - NEW HAVEN RAILROAD, LOCOMOTIVES AND PASSENGER CARS (1955-1956). Marcel Breuer and Associates, Architects; Herbert Matter, Graphic Designs. [Other], (Alternate names: ACF Talgo; Budd; Pullman Train X); See also Boston and Maine Railroad, Locomotive and Passenger Cars.
    - Drawings, 72
      - ACF Talgo Train, details of drinking glass niche (8 Jul 1955): SK. No. 1, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - ACF Talgo Train, elevations and color scheme (31 Aug 1955), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - ACF Talgo Train, hand rail assembly at wheel well (18 Jan 1956), working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - ACF Talgo Train, toilet and vestibule (Void) (13 Jul 1955), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - ACF Talgo Train, toilet plan and elevations (18 Aug 1955), working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - ACF Talgo Train, working drawings (30 Jun 1955-3 Feb 1956), working drawings (originals); 8 (Tube 1178)
      - Budd Train, interior perspective (2 Mar 1956), presentation drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Budd Train, interior perspective (Mar 1956), presentation drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Budd Train, location of identification light and number (10 Feb 1956): SK No. 1, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Budd Train, working drawings (22 Jul 1955-7 Feb 1956): Dwg. Nos. 1-9, working drawings (originals); 11 (Tube 1178)
      - Fairbanks-Morse Locomotive, insignia and painting details (6 Jun 1956), working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Fairbanks-Morse Locomotive, partial side elevation (31 Jan 1956), working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Pullman Train X, Baldwin-Lima-Hamilton Locomotive, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Pullman Train X, Baldwin-Lima-Hamilton Locomotive, design development drawings (reproductions); photostat; 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Pullman Train X, color and pattern, exterior skin (10 Jun 1955), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Pullman Train X, north side elevation, color scheme (16 Jun 1955), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1178)
      - Pullman Train X, presentation sheet [photostat], presentation drawings (reproductions); 2 (Tube 1178)
      - Pullman Train X, working drawings (21 Jun 1955-2 Feb 1956), working drawings (originals); 12 (Tube 1178)
      - All high speed trains, comparative data, presentation drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - All high speed trains, layout for sizes, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - All high speed trains, application of plastic cup holders to seats (17 Oct 1955): Dwg. No. X, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - All high speed trains, insignia and number details (5 Jan 1956-15 Mar 1956), working drawings (originals); 3 (Tube 1179)
      - All high speed trains, plastic cup holders, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - All trains, master key for color designation (22 Nov 1955), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - Bag rack details (19 Oct 1955): Dwg. No. SK1, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - Bag rack details: Dwg. No. SK1 (draft), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - Commuter coach, preliminary drawing (10 Oct 1955): Plan and elevation (Dwg. No. 1), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - Commuter coach, seat plan and window studies, design development drawings (originals); 5 (Tube 1179)
      - Commuter coach, walkover seat (15 Dec 1955): Dwg. No. SK1, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - Commuter coach, working drawings (11 Nov 1955): Dwg. Nos. 1-6, working drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1179)
      - Reclining, reversible seat, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
      - Dwg. No. X-3, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1179)
  - NEW HAVEN RAILROAD, PASSENGER STATION (NEW LONDON, CT), New London, CT (1954-1955) (not built). Marcel Breuer, Architect; Eduardo Catalano, Consultant. [Commercial], (Alternate names: New London Station) See also New Haven Railroad, Passenger Station (Rye, NY).
    - Drawings, 99
      - Design development drawings and sketches, design development drawings (originals and reproductions); includes structural studies for concrete shell, preliminary schemes for station, process prints, plan of existing station; 32 (Tube 1126)
      - Passenger station, New London, Conn. (Aug 1955): Key plan indicating areas of new construction and new traffic routes (Dwg. No. 1); site development and bridge (Dwg. No. 2); elevations and sections of station (Dwg. No. 3/3 "obsolete"); plan of station (Dwg. No. 4/4 "obsolete"); elevations of bridge (Dwg. No. 5); plan of bridge (Dwg. No. 6); concrete shell (Dwg. No. 7), presentation drawings (originals); 9 (Tube 1126)
      - Design development drawings and sketches:, design development drawings (originals); includes alternate viaduct schemes (schemes A and B), parking studies and preliminary site work; 12 (Tube 1127)
      - Proposed Federal Street viaduct and parking, Scheme 1 (25 May 1955): Dwg. Nos. PR.1-PR.9 (no PR.7), presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); reproduction prints with hand coloring and pencil annotations; 8 (Tube 1127)
      - Presentation set: Site development (22 Jun 1955): Dwg. Nos. D1-D12, presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); reproduction prints with hand coloring and pencil annotations; 13 (Tube 1127)
      - Proposed parking facilities plan (25 Oct 1954), presentation drawings (reproductions); includes typed cover sheet; 1 (Tube 1127)
      - Passenger station, New London, Conn (Aug 1955): Key plan indicating areas of new construction and new traffic routes (Dwg. No. 1); site development and bridge (Dwg. No. 2); elevations and sections of station (Dwg. No. 3); plan of station (Dwg. No. 4); elevations of bridge (Dwg. No. 5); plan of bridge (Dwg. No. 6); concrete shell (Dwg. No. 7); proposed viaduct at present R.R. station at New London scheme D (Apr 1955), presentation drawings (reproductions); annotated prints; 8 (Tube 1127)
      - Property affected by new viaduct and re-location of C.V.R.R. Track. 7 (Sep 1955), presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); 1 original drawing and 1 blueprint; 2 (Tube 1127)
      - Property, R.R. track and pavement adjustments in connection with new overpass and parking facilities (9 Dec 1955): Dwg. No. SK-1, presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); 1 original drawing and 2 hand colored print; 3 (Tube 1127)
      - Design development drawings and sketches, design development drawings (reproductions); includes site work, maps and survey material of New London and project site, alternate viaduct schemes (schemes B and C); 11 (Tube 1127)
  - NEW HAVEN RAILROAD, PASSENGER STATION (RYE, NY), Rye, NY (1955-1956) (not built). Marcel Breuer, Architect; Eduardo Catalano, Consultant. [Other], (Alternate names: Rye Station); See also New Haven Railroad, Passenger Station (New London, CT).
    - Drawings, 32
      - Preliminary site plan, design development drawings (reproductions); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Dimensions of No.11 phone booth, other drawings (hybrids); reproduced product specifications with pencil annotations; 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Rendered perspective of station building with view toward platform, presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); 1 original and 1 print; 2 (Tube 1144)
      - Traffic pattern studies for circulation around station: Schemes No. 1-3, design development drawings (hybrids); 6 (Tube 1144)
      - Preliminary Sketch: Full Scale details of furring on metal partitions in executive offices, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Details of furring on metal partitions in executive offices (9 Jan 1956): Dwg. No. SK1, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Preliminary plan (26 Apr 1956), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Revised plan (5 Jul 1956), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Sketches of toilet layouts, design development drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1144)
      - Typical exterior window details (22 May 1956), design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Project sketches: Plan layouts, design development drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1144)
      - Plan (22 Jun 1956), design development drawings (originals); marked "Void" and "Issued as Progress Drawings Only"; 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Construction set: Site plan, plans, elevations, details (Sheet Nos. 1-6), working drawings (originals); 6 (Tube 1144)
      - Structural details (24 Aug 1956), working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Heating and ventilating, plumbing (24 Aug 1956): Sheet No. M1, working drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1144)
      - Electrical, mechanical (24 Aug 1956): Sheet Nos. E1, ME1, working drawings (hybrids); 2 (Tube 1144)
    - Project files
      - Correspondence: Consultants (1956), George E. Strehan, Engineers and Architects (Box 127, Folder 16)
  - NEW YORK UNIVERSITY BUILDING COMPLEX, UNIVERSITY HEIGHTS CAMPUS, New York, NY (1956-1969). Marcel Breuer and Associates, Architects. [Educational]
    (Alternate names: Bronx Community College (CUNY))
    See also New York University Residence Hall; New York University Student Center; New York University Technology I; New York University Technology II.
    - Drawings, 120
      - Aerial perspective of campus, presentation drawings (originals); graphite on vellum mounted on board, 17 x 24 in.; 1 (Map-case 113, Folder 4)
      - Perspective rendering: Dormitory (1965), presentation drawings (originals); graphite, pen and ink on illustration board, 14 x 20 in.; 1 (Map-case 113, Folder 3)
      - Interior perspective of library, presentation drawings (originals); window-mounted color rendering with montage, 22.5 x 29 in.; 1 (Map-case 113, Folder 7)
      - Interior perspective of classroom, presentation drawings (originals); window-mounted color rendering with montage, 22.5 x 29 in.; 1 (Map-case 113, Folder 6)
      - Aerial perspective of campus, presentation drawings (originals); graphite on vellum mounted on board, 13 x 29 in.; 1 (Map-case 113, Folder 2)
      - Presentation set, comprehensive plan: Plates I-IV, presentation drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1474)
      - Presentation set, exiting buildings, new construction Program areas, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1474)
      - Miscellaneous presentation sheets, presentation drawings (originals); legends, cover sheets and cut-outs used to make presentation sets; 5 (Tube 1474)
      - Design development drawings and studies related to comprehensive plan, site analysis/planning and long range development (Jul 1956-Feb 1963), design development drawings (originals and reproductions); 61 originals and 43 prints; 104 (Tube 1266-1267)
    - Project files
      - Bid documents and notices (1959) (Box 135, Folder 1)
    - Photographs, 83
      - Construction progress photos of Begrisch Hall, Technology Building, Residence Hall, Student Center, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; most with captions; 70 (Box 135, Folder 2-3)
      - Construction progress photos of Begrisch Hall, Technology Building, Residence Hall, Student Center, construction, exterior view; negatives; 9 (Box 135, Folder 2)
      - Construction progress photos of Begrisch Hall, Technology Building, Residence Hall, Student Center, construction, exterior view; contact sheets; 4 (Box 135, Folder 2)
  - NEW YORK UNIVERSITY RESIDENCE HALL, UNIVERSITY HEIGHTS CAMPUS, New York, NY (1954-1965). Marcel Breuer, Architect; Robert F. Gatje, Associate. [Educational], (Alternate names: Silver Hall; Colston Hall; Student Dormitory); See also New York University Building Complex; New York University Student Center; New York University Technology I; New York University Technology II.
    - Drawings, 692
      - Presentation sheets: Site plan, perspective renderings and typical dorm room, presentation drawings (reproductions); 4 (Tube 1269)
      - Presentation set, new dormitory for New York University (Jan 1958): Sheet Nos. 1-6, presentation drawings (originals and reproductions; 1 set of 6 originals, 1 set of 6 prints and 2 miscellaneous duplicate prints; 14 (Tube 1269)
      - Student dormitory (15 Jan 1960): (Dwg. Nos. DS-1, DS-2, DS-4): Revisions to retaining wall, working drawings (originals); 3 (Tube 1269)
      - Construction set (5 Dec 1958): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. 1-27); boring (Dwg. Nos. B1-B6); structural (Dwg. Nos. S1-S18), working drawings (reproductions); marked "desk copy"; 45 (Tube 217)
      - Construction set (15 Dec 1958): Heating and ventilation (Dwg. Nos. HV1-HV12); kitchen plans (Dwg. No. K1); plumbing (Dwg. Nos. P1-P11); plumbing utilities (Dwg. Nos. UP1-UP3); electrical (Dwg. Nos. E1-E14), working drawings (reproductions); marked "desk copy"; 41 (Tube 218)
      - Construction set, earlier scheme (1 Apr 1954) (Eggers and Higgins, Architects): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. 100-114); structural (Dwg. Nos. S501-S505), working drawings (reproductions); very fragile; 21 (Tube 219)
      - Construction set (15 Dec 1958): Heating and ventilation (Dwg. Nos. HV1-HV12); kitchen plans (Dwg. No. K1); plumbing (Dwg. Nos. P1-P11); plumbing utilities (Dwg. Nos. UP1-UP3); electrical (Dwg. Nos. E1-E14), working drawings (reproductions); marked "office copy: bid set"; 41 (Tube 220)
      - Construction set (15 Dec 1958): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. 2-25); electrical vault (Dwg. No. SK1); structural (Dwg. Nos. S1-S13, S15-S18), working drawings (reproductions); annotated prints with sketches on back of some sheets; 41 (Tube 221)
      - Revised kitchen area (May 1960): Dwg. Nos. 3R, P11A, HV9A, E13A, plan of piping connections, working drawings (reproductions); some duplicate sheets; 7 (Tube 221)
      - Construction set (15 Dec 1958): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. 1-27); heating and ventilation (Dwg. Nos. HV1-HV12), working drawings (reproductions); marked "Architect's Record set"; 39 (Tube 222)
      - Construction set (15 Dec 1958): Heating and ventilation (Dwg. Nos. HV1-HV12); kitchen plans (Dwg. No. K1); plumbing (Dwg. Nos. P1-P11); plumbing utilities (Dwg. Nos. UP1-UP3); electrical (Dwg. Nos. E1-E14), structural (Dwg. No. S12), working drawings (reproductions); "Housing Home Finance Agency" stamp on verso; 42 (Tube 223)
      - Construction set contract drawings (15 Dec 1958): plumbing (Dwg. Nos. P1-P11); kitchen plans (Dwg. No. K1); plumbing utilities (Dwg. Nos. UP1-UP3); electrical (Dwg. Nos. E1-E14); boring (Dwg. Nos. B1-B6); structural (Dwg. Nos. S1-S18), working drawings (reproductions); "approved as to form" 15 Apr 1959; 53 (Tube 224)
      - Construction set contract drawings (15 Dec 1958): Architectural (Dwg. Nos. 1-27); boring (Dwg. Nos. B1-B6); structural (Dwg. Nos. S1-S18), working drawings (reproductions); marked "executed"; 51 (Tube 225)
      - Construction set (15 Dec 1958): architectural (Dwg. Nos. 1-27); structural (Dwg. Nos. S1-S18), working drawings (originals); 45 (Tube 1271)
      - Construction set (15 Dec 1958): Heating and ventilation (Dwg. Nos. HV1-HV12); kitchen plans (Dwg. No. K1); plumbing (Dwg. Nos. P1-P11); plumbing utilities (Dwg. Nos. UP1-UP3); electrical (Dwg. Nos. E1-E14), working drawings (originals); 41 (Tube 1272)
      - Design development drawings (Oct 1957-Oct 1959): Residence hall (Dwg. Nos. R1-R45 incomplete, and unnumbered), design development drawings (originals); includes preliminary plot plan, floor plan studies, window details, penthouse and bulkhead schemes, connecting bridge, typical room studies, masonry details, stair plans and details, column details, core layout, wall section studies, kitchen plan, cabinet details; 98 (Tube 1273)
      - Submission to Housing and Home Finance Agency (30 Oct 1957): Plans, elevations, site plan (Sheet Nos. 1-2), presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1273)
      - Dormitory for New York University: Preliminary design (circa Nov 1957): Sheet Nos. 1-2 and plot diagram, presentation drawings (originals); 3 (Tube 1273)
      - Preliminary residence hall sunscreen (Sep 1958): Dwg. Nos. S46 and S46A, presentation drawings (originals); 2 (Tube 1273)
      - Open center floor scheme (7 Nov 1957), presentation drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1273)
      - Design development drawings (Apr-Oct 1958): Community Hall (Nos. C5-C21 incomplete and unnumbered), design development drawings (originals); includes lighting details, plan studies, plans, connecting bridge, entry details, subframe details, typical sections, toilet and stair details; 24 (Tube 1273)
      - Mechanical and structural shop drawings, residence hall and community hall (circa Jun-Sep 1958), design development drawings (reproductions); includes annotated prints; 9 (Tube 1273)
      - Boring report and data sheets (Jun 1958), design development drawings (reproductions); 8 (Tube 1273)
      - Design development sketches and drawings (Feb 1958-Jun 1965), design development drawings (originals and reproductions); includes site work, retaining wall, parking garage, electrical vault, typical room studies and interior details, plan studies, section studies, elevation studies, sketch renderings; 50 originals and 2 prints; 52 (Tube 1270)
      - New York University dormitory garage (14 May 1965): Schemes A-D, design development drawings (originals); 4 (Tube 1270)
      - Preliminary design submission (21 Nov 1957): Dwg. No. 3, design development drawings (originals); 1 (Tube 1270)
    - Photographs, For additional photographs of this project, see also New York University Building Complex: Photographs; New York University Technology I: Photographs; 95
      - Excavation and foundation work (1959): Residence Hall and Technology I, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 11 (Box 135, Folder 4)
      - Construction progress photos (1960): Residence Hall and Technology I, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 44 (Box 135, Folder 5)
      - Construction progress photos (1961): Residence Hall, Student Center, Begrisch Hall and Technology I, construction, exterior view; black and white photographs; 24 (Box 135, Folder 6)
      - View looking north-east, finished project, exterior view; black and white photograph; board mounted; 1 (Box 135, Folder 6)
      - Connecting bridge [Roll 6, Frame 1], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Elevated walk [Roll 6, Frame 2], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Connecting bridge [Roll 6, Frame 3], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Connecting bridge [Roll 6, Frame 4], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Connecting bridge [Roll 6, Frame 5], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Elevated walk [Roll 6, Frame 6], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Connecting bridge [Roll 6, Frame 7], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Connecting bridge [Roll 6, Frame 8], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Residence Hall [Roll 6, Frame 12], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Residence Hall [Roll 6, Frame 17], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Connecting bridge [Roll 6, Frame 18], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Elevated walk [Roll 6, Frame 19], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Residence Hall [Roll 6, Frame 20], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Residence Hall [Roll 6, Frame 36], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Residence Hall [Roll 8, Frame 20], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-15)
  - NEW YORK UNIVERSITY STUDENT CENTER, UNIVERSITY HEIGHTS CAMPUS, New York, NY (1959-1961). Marcel Breuer, Architect; Robert F. Gatje, Associate. [Educational]
    (Alternate names: Community Hall)
    See also New York University Building Complex; New York University Residence Hall; New York University Technology I; New York University Technology II.
    - Drawings
      See New York University Residence Hall.
    - Photographs, 4
      For additional photographs of this project, see also New York University Building Complex: Photographs; New York University Residence Hall: Photographs; New York University Technology I: Photographs
      - Student Center [Roll 6, Frame 13], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Student Center [Roll 6, Frame 15], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Student Center [Roll 6, Frame 16], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-14)
      - Student Center [Roll 8, Frame 22], construction, exterior view; negative; 1 (Box SL-15)
  - NEW YORK UNIVERSITY TECHNOLOGY I, UNIVERSITY HEIGHTS CAMPUS, New York, NY (1956-1961). Marcel Breuer, Architect; Hamilton P. Smith, Associate. [Educational], (Alternate names: Begrisch Hall; Gould Hall of Technology; Polowczyk Hall; NYU Tech I); See also New York University Building Complex; New York University Residence Hall; New York University Student Center; New York University Technology II.
    - Drawings, 702
      - Westinghouse Science Hall (20 Jan 1958): Preliminary scheme, presentation drawings (originals and reproductions); 1 original and 1 print; 2 (Tube 1274)